<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some papers writ in the year 1664 In answer to a letter, concerning the practice of physick in England. By Dr. C. T. Published at the request of a friend and several fellows of the College of Physicians.</title>
            <author>Terne, Christopher, 1620-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2099:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some papers writ in the year 1664 In answer to a letter, concerning the practice of physick in England. By Dr. C. T. Published at the request of a friend and several fellows of the College of Physicians.</title>
                  <author>Terne, Christopher, 1620-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Allestry, at the Rose and Crown, in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXX. [1670]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C. T. = Christopher Terne (cf. Wing).</note>
                  <note>With errata on A4v.</note>
                  <note>Copy has MS. attribution on title page: "Tim Clarke".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pharmacists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physicians --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME PAPERS Writ in the Year 1664.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a LETTER, Concerning the <hi>PRACTICE of PHYSICK</hi> IN ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>By Dr. <hi>C. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of a Friend and ſeveral Fellows of the College of Phyſicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Alleſtry,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> MDCLXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36531:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36531:2"/>
            <head>For my Worthy and much Honoured Friend the Author of the following Diſcourſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Own a very great Obligation for thoſe Papers you were pleaſed to entruſt me with ſo freely as you did, and at the firſt requeſt; and though it be now five or ſix years ſince you writ them, yet I know they will be hugely welcome to the publick; and the World will be informed, that what is now proſecuted, is in truth a matter of conſequence, and not a caprice of young un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practis'd heads, as ſome endeavour to render it, but managed ſeriouſly by men of the ableſt of the Profeſſion, and worthy of the care and conſideration of our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. And pray give me leave in a few words to acquaint you with the occaſion I had to deſire them of you at firſt.</p>
            <p>It was my good fortune not long ſince to be in the Company of five or ſix perſons, not only conſiderable for their Eſtates and Intereſt in the City, but likewiſe for their mature underſtanding of buſineſs: as they were diſcourſing of ſeueral matters relating to the Trade both of the City and Nation in general, it happened that one paſt through the room in which they ſat, to go up a pair of ſtairs that lead into a Chamber, where the only Son of the Gentleman, at whoſe Houſe they were, then lay under ſome little Aguiſh diſtemper: One of
<pb facs="tcp:36531:3"/> the Company that ſpyed him, ſaluted him by his name, which occaſioned another to demand who it was; to whom the Gentleman of the Houſe replyed, it was his Apothecary gone up to viſit his Son who was at that time a little indiſpoſed; whereupon another ask't the reſt if they had ſeen two Diſcourſes lately publiſht by two very eminent Members of the College of Phyſicians, which (ſays he) the Apothecary's paſſing by put me in mind of: one beſides himſelf, ſaid he had ſeen and read them, and added frankly, they ſeemed in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment very judiciouſly writ, and very much to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by all that regarded their healths; ſo they left off a little their former diſcourſe, and began to enter into the matter of thoſe Books, and the perſons that read them repreſented to the Company, ſome of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant paſſages, as their memories ſerved: whilſt they were thus diſcourſing, the Apothecary came down, and was called by the Maſter of the Houſe to this part of their Conference: To do him right, he ſpoke very ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy, and told the Gentlemen he hoped all theſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of difference between the Colledge and them would ſoon paſs over, and preſently took leave and went away. After he was gone, one among the reſt, a very grave man, who had ſat all the while ſilent and heard what was produc't out of theſe Books, began very ſolemnly to declare, that ſince health was one of the greateſt goods of life, and that which alone gives as it were their being ſo, to all the reſt; and ſince it was ſo much the intereſt of a Prince to preſerve his people in ſtrength and vigour, he profeſt he could not underſtand how that reconcilement of theſe differences between the Phyſicians and the Apothecaries, which ſo much concern
<pb facs="tcp:36531:3"/> the lives and healths of the Kings Subjects, could ever be ſo well made up as the perſon that was gone ſaid he hoped to ſee. For, ſaid he, if what has been alledged out of theſe Books here, be true, there has been too long already a foul and ſhameful abuſe put upon the people, by the preſent method of practiſing Phyſick, as it now (ſo he phraſed it) joggs on between the Phyſician and Apothecary, and that ſince thoſe able and well-known Phyſicians had ſo freely and honeſtly of themſelves propoſed ways of redreſs, and ſo far opened the eyes of all men to diſcern the mockeries they have been gulled with ſo long, he ſaid it was too late for them now eaſily to retreat: And believed that all men who had read thoſe Books would as well as he, look upon ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, as a new way only of continuing the former abuſes under ſome more artificial and ſecret diſguiſe. But whatever, ſaid he, may be done out of Conſcience, I am ſure they ſhall deſtroy their intereſt by it, and as long as ever Apothecaries continue practiſing as they do, ſo long ſhall the moſt gainful and ſecure part of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice come into their hands, by means of the Bills they formerly have, and daily will receive from them, and nothing remain for the Phyſician but ſuch ſollicitous and extream Caſes (where the Apothecary ſhall vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to call him in) in which his own credit ſhall every moment run as great a fortune as the Patients life. For, ſaid he, how many men in this Town have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, or ever ſhall be intended by the Phyſicians as Apothecaries only, we in ſpight of common courſe they now take to hinder it, ſhall to ſave charge and expence of Phyſick, always eſteem and make uſe of as a ſort of cheaper Doctors; except only in ſuch extremities
<pb facs="tcp:36531:4"/> where our lives are in manifeſt danger. And I have often wondred that ſo great a Company of prudent men ſhould do ſuch things every day, which if we in our particular Trades ſhould ſuffer, we ſhould not only be laught at, but others of the ſame way would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently endeavour to obſtruct or puniſh. For I have often obſerved my ſelf (to tell truth) when I have been with my Phyſician either for my own concern or any of my Family, and have received good by what has been preſcribed; my Apothecary has often recommended the ſame, and repeated it again without the knowledg of the Doctor; and at other times told my Wife of an excellent courſe againſt the Scurvy, ordered by an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Phyſician, and named him: and ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended a Powder of another Doctors againſt the Worms, for my Children, which he ſaid he had by him: All which things I noted to be ſo prejudicial to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, that I could not chooſe but wonder that Phyſicians would ſo careleſly expoſe the fruit of all their time and ſtudies, and put every day the beſt of their Trade out of their own hands into anothers who had ſo little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of them: And this indeed wholly deterred me from breeding one of my Sons a Phyſician, ſince I ſaw how eaſily every good Medicine that my Doctor had, came into the hands of my Apothecary for a fee or two, and after that, both I and all my Friends could readily command it, and Mr. Doctor never the wiſer.</p>
            <p>When this Gentleman had done, we began freely to tell one another, being all Tradeſmen, who knew as well the difficulty of getting, as the uſe and conſequence of money, how it was cuſtomary with us to ſend to our Apothecaries only, unleſs where the danger was very
<pb facs="tcp:36531:4"/> great, to avoid the charge and expence of Phyſicians: Not but that we all concluded it would be better to have the advice of a Phyſician at the very firſt, if they would ſo order the matter that we might addreſs our ſelves as reaſonably to them as we now can to our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary; foraſmuch as the greateſt diſeaſes have ſmall beginnings, and it were more comfortable to apply our ſelves where we may be as well adviſed of the nature of our preſent indiſpoſition and what it is like to come to, as receive what is proper, either to cure or prevent it, which ſaid they, on all hands is confeſt, the Phyſician is more able to do than an Apothecary, elſe ſhould we never fly to him where we fear a danger as now we do. I then took occaſion to tell them, that the principal deſign aimed at in thoſe Books was to exhibit ſuch a method as might leſſen the expence of Phyſick to the people more then half in half, and to ſhew that the Apothecary by his exceſſive prices, and by his unneceſſary and frequent repetitions of chargeable Medicines, beſides ſees which ſome of them take, and expect, or elſe they think they are not kindly uſed, amounted often to three times as much as they could hope to have ſaved in fees by not going to the Phyſician; and farther added, that a worthy Friend of mine a Phyſician had an excellent diſcourſe by him to advance this propoſition, and enforce what had been already made publick. They commanded me to importune you for it, which ſince you are pleaſed ſo readily to conſent to, you have a great deal more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged all the World in it than me, although I am as much as any can be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate and obliged Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:36531:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 9. lin. 18. read Fevers. lin. 25. Phyſician, pag. 13. lin. 24. r. moſt of us have been Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers. p. 17. l. 11. r. they would. p. 35. the laſt line, r. by Cuſtom, and leave out the following by, pag. 37. l. 18. r. their, p. 41. l. 9. r. it proved, p. 43. l. 4. that Roman, p. 46. l. 4. <hi>Prujean.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36531:5"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Doe aſſure you I defer much to your kindneſs, or to your judgement, or to both, in that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented you ſhould do what you will with part of <hi>thoſe papers I writt in</hi> 64 but ſince ſome of thoſe people who <hi>invaded the profeſſion of Phyſick, and railed at learning and the Colledge</hi> (with all that confidence that great ignorance uſes to enable bold Knaves with) are dead, or ſunk into that contempt ſuch men at laſt muſt fall into, I would have all that which concerns their Charecters wholly left out, nor am I at all willing that the reformation of our faculty, which I there deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhould as yet be made publick.</p>
               <p>For although I have been ſeveral times confirmed by better judgements than my own, that it is a rational way to improve the uſefullneſſe of our profeſſion, as much as by the induſtry of a Society of men learned and moſt capable of ſuch an undertaking, it is poſſible to be done, yet I do not think the age, or the world we live in, very ſuſceptible of ſuch propoſitions now.</p>
               <p>The Charity there deſigned to ſupply all the poor of <hi>the Cities of London and Weſtminſter</hi> with advice, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36531:6"/> ſome of them with medicines <hi>gratis,</hi> and the better ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and ſerving the ſick in thoſe Hoſpitals we have, would but be looked upon as a decoy to bring in bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours, whoſe bounty and Charity might be perverted to luxurious uſes, and the care that is offered at to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt the ſlaughters every day made <hi>by ignorant Quacks and Mountebancks,</hi> and yet to ſecure all the encouragements that can reaſonably be asked to any that are really poſſeſſed of any thing that may be uſeful to the recovery or comfort of thoſe that are afflicted with ſickneſs, would be looked upon but as a deſign to Monopoliſe phyſick to <hi>the Colledge,</hi> and to inveſt the Phyſitians with a power to enſlave <hi>Chyrurgeons and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas Sir, we live in an age where to preſcribe any bounds is <hi>to violate magna Charta,</hi> we would all be <hi>Kings</hi> but <hi>Stateſ-men</hi> we are all, nor can any of thoſe that are really ſo, with ſo much confidence, venture to cure any diſeaſe in a man, as the blew aprons in a Coffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe ſhall all thoſe in the State, for it is the humour now to affect, to be wiſeſt out of the Sphear that <hi>God, Nature, and Education have placed us in,</hi> and we all think ourſelves able, and are buſie to reforme every thing, but that which is really our duty to endeavour the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of, I am ſure you cannot but meet with occaſions every day to confirme theſe obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>And this I confeſs makes me think diverſly from what I finde the general opinion to be, That it is an age for the advancement and improvement of knowledge; I rather fear our tumbling into the greateſt barbarity and the moſt profound ignorance, the way to ſolid know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36531:6"/> by cultivating of our reaſons, and inuring them to compare, compute, and eſtimate well, begins now to be wholly deſpiſed, the young blades who have tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anted at School, and debauched at an Univerſity, if they have acquired but rongue enough to rally the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient learning, and talk of experiments, will diſturbe the graveſt Societies with their impertinenties, ſilence the moſt learned, and think themſelves the only dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in univerſal learning, and if they are ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to be endowed with wit and good natural parts, <hi>they turn every thing that is ſober into Ridiculous, and go out Doctors in Atheiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our municipal Lawyers have a bar that hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to kept ignorant invaders at ſome diſtance in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but Women, Weavers and Coblers think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able to comprehend all the myſteries in Divinity, and all the reaſon of Phyſick, Zeal and good meaning may excuſe them in their Divinity but I am deceived if any thing, but pride, and the greateſt folly, can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for their Phyſick.</p>
               <p>How authoritatively will a Nurſe with winde and vapours give you the cauſes of all diſeaſes and their Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes, but <hi>an Apothecaries Prentice</hi> with Fermentation confounds the admiring Cuſtomers, who take him for a very prieſt of <hi>Apollo</hi> pronouncing from his Tripode, whileſt a <hi>learned and a rational Phyſitian,</hi> eſpecially if he have the misfortune of being modeſt, is looked upon at the beſt but as a weak, and a timorous man, if he hath the good fortune to be counted a ſafe man, he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have ſome few patients, but the Crowdes for the moſt part follow the boaſting and the lying Quacks; and although they find themſelves ſtill cheated by them,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36531:7"/> yet a new one or the ſame with ſome circumſtances a little diſguiſed ſhall cheate them over again, how often even in our age, hath the cheats and knaveries of the pretended Chymiſts been detected, even with the ruin of ſome of the admirers of it, yet that vanity wants not its Patrons now: and ſober men who knowing the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs of Chymiſtry, and the beſt wayes of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, would purge it from that lying and knavery which makes the very enquiring into it a reproach in the opinion of ſome ſober men, are looked upon as not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of knowing any thing in it, ſo that with ſome men a man muſt not be thought a Chymiſt without renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing learning and his reaſon, and with others he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to have ſhaken-hands with them and honeſty to, if they think him one. I have a great many more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why I would not have that part of my diſcourſe printed truly I have enough too that nothing of it ſhould be, ſince I believe that there is very little ſaid in that which hath not been better ſaid by others: Beſides when I writ it, the letter wich gave the occaſion of it was juſt printed, and in every ones hand, which would have a little ſatisfied, for the immethodicalneſs of the anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; The provocations <hi>the Apothecaries</hi> had given us were very freſh, they endeavour, dirtily and unjuſtly <hi>to aſperſe that Society of men who gave them that Trade, by which they were grown rich, and had the Confidence to affront the Kings prerogative in oppoſing our patent,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that prerogative is the only title they have to be a Corporation: The pretended Chymiſts were then ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up for a Colledge to lay in a Magazine of charcoale, that they might have the better utterance for ſmoak and lyes, and to ſhew how uſeful they might in time be,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36531:7"/> did every day furniſh us with ſome papers for neceſſary uſes, but all that being ſpent and the reſt almoſt forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the heat I then was in is much cooled, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I would rather contribute to the preſerving <hi>the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries,</hi> than the deſtroying of them, ſo it may be done honeſtly, but we cannot be honeſt men if we do in the leaſt connive at their abuſing the people in their Quacking, or the priſes of their medicines, nor can they be honeſt when they meddle in what they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, and unjuſtly injure thoſe men to whom they owe their being <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> To make this very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent is but briefly and truly to ſtare the caſe betwixt us and them.</p>
               <p>Although <hi>the Colledge of Phyſitians</hi> had been eſtabliſhed <hi>in the Reign of King Henry the 8th</hi> under the broad ſeal of <hi>England,</hi> and was confirmed by ſeveral acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet there was no ſuch thing as a Corporation of the Trade of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> until the <hi>Reign of King Iames,</hi> when the Colledge (I hope not through pride and laſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs grown weary of making their own medicines, but) to obviate all the miſchiefs that might be done, where the ordainers of medicines were the makers and exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of them too, petitioned the King, that ſuch a number of men whoſe names they offered might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the moſt part, I think out of the company of Grocers, and conſtituted a company diſtinct; <hi>for the making ſuch medicines as the Colledge of Phyſitians ſhould ordain,</hi> this petition was granted, and they by the Kings Charter made a Corporation, and in that Charter there is ſpecial proviſion made, <hi>that nothing in it ſhould in the leaſt infringe the priviledges of the Colledge of Phyſitians,</hi> the inventing, ordaining, and making of medicines
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36531:8"/> having alwayes been a part of Phyſick, and ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly aſſerted in the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> conſtitution, <hi>that by the Kings eſpecial command the Colledge of Phyſitians compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the London diſpenſatory, and the Apothecaries not only of London but of all England are, by publick proclamation, commanded to follow that, as the rule of their Trade, they are to make and ſell thoſe medicines in their ſhops, and the Phyſitians impowred to ſearch and examine thoſe ſhops, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have them, and have them well made: They have not the leaſt clauſe in their Charter to enable them to adviſe, preſcribe or ordainany remedy, but they are faithfully to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe ſuch medicines as ſhall be ordered by Phyſitians, and are not to make a Prentice free without his being firſt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Phyſitians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was upon theſe termes <hi>the Colledge</hi> truſted <hi>the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries</hi> with the knowledge of making their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and let it be left now to any indifferent man to judge what the honeſty or gratitude of thoſe men can be, who not only betray a truſt, committed to them with ſo much advantage to themſelves, but convert what they are truſted with to the hurt of thoſe that truſt them.</p>
               <p>I ſhould have thought this enough to have impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated the matter betwixt them and us, if I had not lately read as ridiculous a peice of drollery in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as no ſenſe, leſs reaſon, and great confidence can furniſh out, nothing can ſpeak more pride nor more ignorance; which two in conjunction do alwayes inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently endeavour to level every thing to the meaneſs of their own underſtandings. I would have <hi>the Pulpit guard routed,</hi> and this witty pamphlet called <hi>Lex Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lionis or Vinditiae</hi> printed together, to ſhow the uſeleſsneſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36531:8"/> of thoſe tedious methods of ſtudying divinity, and Phyſick, and how unneceſſary the endowments of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, Colledges and Schools are. The civil law hath no great encouragements left amongſt us, and if the Butcher, the Cobler, the Weaver with gifts are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to preach and teach than the men of humane learning, and carnal knowledge; and if ſerving an Apprentiſhip ſeven years vvith an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> and reading a little in thoſe three ancient Authors <hi>Frambeſarius, Riverius and Primroſe,</hi> qualifies any man ſufficiently for the practice of Phyſick, to what end this charge and trouble of taking degrees, this twelve years ſtudy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man can be a Doctor. The learning to know all homebred and exotick plants, the Analyſing of them in their Elaboratories, the conſidering vvhat parts are uſeful of them, and vvhat not, and how their effects may beſt, and moſt gratefully be acquired, the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the beſt vvays of compounding and mixing (vvhich are things I am ſure the Students in Phyſick in both our Univerſities for ſome years paſt have buſied themſelves with) are nothing to what may be acquired by making of medicines, according to the Diſpenſatory, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to the beſt advantage: but although this Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal hath ſhewed his teeth thus againſt Learning and the Univerſities, and may perhaps, becauſe he could not bite, paſs unpuniſhed by them, ſure the Apothecaries have more ſenſe than not to find him out, and puniſh him for his moſt ſcandalous libelling of them, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their fortune may be otherwiſe, I cannot think a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſo fooliſhly wicked as to be Wittals, nor ſo wretchedly knaviſh to ſuffer the Phyſitians to go ſnips with them in their profits, the better to cheat their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36531:9"/> which this thing of paper vvould inſinuate to the World that ſome of them do.</p>
               <p>But the poor Droll had not ſenſe enough to knovv, that making of Cuckolds and getting of mony are not by all accounted very diſgracefull crimes, by vvhat inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſoever the pleaſure or the profit is procured, nor did his little underſtanding comprehend hovv vvret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly contemptible thoſe inſtruments of either are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thoſe vvhoſe bad ends they ſerve, ſure <hi>the honeſt Apothecaries</hi> (and I cannot but perſvvade my ſelf there are many ſuch) vvhen they conſider that this inſiped libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler having inſinuated, that there are <hi>ſome Apothecaries,</hi> vvho are ſuch vvretched inſtruments for the profit and pleaſure of Phyſitians, and not particularly marked them out; hath given the cenſuring part of the World occaſion to think every <hi>Apothecary</hi> ſuch an one: vvill rouſe themſelves, and either by publickly branding the Guilty, vindicate the Innocent; or elſe by perſuing the ſottiſh Defamor to a juſt puniſhment, doe ſome-thing tovvards vviping off thoſe dirty aſperſions he hath caſt upon them.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Phyſitians that think any thing in the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet reflects on them, may by making their ovvn me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and having as little to do vvith <hi>Apothecaries</hi> as may be, teſtify to all the World that they are not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy vvith diſhoneſty, and the vvorld vvill eaſily be ſatisfied that it is cheaper being couſened by one than by tvvo, and that it is much ſafer to truſt him vvhoſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and intereſt it is to cure Diſeaſes, than him vvhoſe intereſt is only to put off his vvare. But let the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> vindicate themſelves as vvell as they can, this fellovv being believed to be <hi>an Apothecary</hi> (and truly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36531:9"/> the ſtile, the method, and the force of his reaſoning ſeem to make good the Proverb, that <hi>he talks as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi>) hath left that ſcandal upon them and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, they will not be able eaſily to wipe off, for it will be believed he knew what he ſaid, at leaſt as to his own particular, and vvas therefore vvilling enough to have the World believe the ſame of all the reſt of his profeſſion; he ſhould therefore have done vvell to have given his Book a truer Title, <hi>Scandalum Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopaerum</hi> had been much fitter for it than <hi>Vindiciae &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, I am grown almoſt as impertinent as he, and although I have already out-run the limits of a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I cannot give over vvithout telling you, I think you did not do, your ſelf, nor our faculty right, in that you did not better inform the grave company you ſpake off; you knovv as vvell as I, that it is an experiment as old as <hi>Gallen</hi> (who with the ſame medicines cured fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Rome</hi> vvith vvhich ſome of the Roman Practitioners killed men) that not only the more generous and powerful remedies, but the vveaker and milder have when unduely made uſe off, brought on irreparable miſchiefs: I do aſſure you vve have ſome very late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of it, vvhere the Apothecaries Quacking with medicines formerly preſcribed by the Phyſitians, and he at laſt, though too late called in has had the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to ſee his patient die, and his medicines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed, vvhileſt the Apothecarv to juſtify himſelf, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed he had given nothing but vvhat the Phyſitlan in the ſame caſe before ordained, whileſt the mifera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wretch had not only wholy miſtaken the caſe, but moſt unduly exhibited the remedies: We are able to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36531:10"/> produce many miſcarriages of this kind, and indeed I think it a duty incumbent upon us, to make things of this nature as publick as vve can, for vvhileſt vve detect all the fraudes and abuſes that men may ſuffer by, in the ill uſing of Phyſick, and do our ovvn parts to the beſt of our underſtanding honeſtly, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndidly, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably vvhere our aſſiſtance is required, vve deliver our ovvn Souls, and then in Gods name let every man diſpoſe of the care of his ovvn life and health as to him ſeemes beſt.</p>
               <p>But Sir, it is time that I releaſe you, and if you will be Printing theſe Papers, remember I cannot think them worth the owning, eſpecially after what hath been ſaid in this kind already.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ALthough I was extreamly pleaſed with the news of your ſafe arrival, yet that of the improvement <hi>of that noble Ladies health</hi> by what I ſent her, gives me ſo great and pleaſing a ſatisfaction as you only can gueſs at; who know the zealous deſignes I have to ſerve her as ſuccesfully as I am ſure I do faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>But the compoſition and making of that ſyrrup which <hi>my Lady</hi> hath found ſo much good by, and of divers others out of the common road, are the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of an order lately made at a full Colledge amongſt us, to encourage all of our profeſſion to the making
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36531:10"/> of medicines for their own practice, and to which if the members of our Society will induſtriouſly ſettle themſelves: <hi>as I doubt not but we ſhall acquire all thoſe noble ends you mention in your Letter, and which as I go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long I ſhall particularly ſpeak to, ſo it will be the beſt way to brand thoſe men for their injuſtice, and ingratitude, who have had the confidence publickly to affirme that they who made and taught them their profeſſion were wholly ignorant in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do aſſure you Sir it is with ſome reluctancy that I tell you, that we believe that we are able to pick out, divers Mrs. amongſt them of name; that appear full of buſineſs, but are really full of words, and yet are whollv ignorant, in thoſe firſt and ſimple preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of infuſions: and others, who by their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, have been forced after they have ſet up for themſelves, to take Journeymen, to teach them how to make up the common medicines of the <hi>Diſpenſatory,</hi> their Mrs. not having the will, or leaſure (to ſay no other) to teach it them, in the whole time of their Apprentiſhips.</p>
               <p>But Sir as your own obſervations amongſt men, have given you occaſion enough to remark the bold ignorance, of many of theſe invaders of our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo they have amongſt things too, taught you, how divers the laws of drawing out Tinctures exactly are, as to their proper menſtruums, time, and heat, ſo that you cannot much wonder at <hi>my Ladys complaint:</hi> That <hi>Apothecaries ignorant or careleſs in theſe things, make up theſe ſorts of medicines you mention, ſo fullſome, nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous, and unhealthy,</hi> but this not being my buſineſs at this time, I ſhall proceed with your letter.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:36531:11"/>
               <p>And ſhould Sir with you and your good company, heartily bewaile the State of the profeſſors of Phyſick at preſent in this nation, if my humour and Philoſophy, as you very well know, did not aſſigne me rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the followers of <hi>Democritus</hi> than <hi>Heraclitus;</hi> I conſeſs I cannot forbear ſmiling at the ſcarce credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble humour that reignes now amongſt ſome men, that are certainly no friends to inſpiration, new lights nor levelling, of patronizing thoſe, who if they have any knowledge in Phyſick, it muſt be from inſpiration or new light, which ſome of them indeed pretend to, for as to any proper education to what they profeſs, they are too well knovvn to make any clame here, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or ſcholaſtick education they publickly declaim againſt, they rail at Anatomical exerciſes as uſeleſs, and think the knovvledge of plants, fit only for an herb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife to make and ſell Noſegays with, the Groom of the Chamber of whom you ſhall hear more anon, tells you but with reverence to God Almighty, that he might have ſpared his labour, of making all that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful variety of medicinal plants, ſince he knoweth a ſeperating medicine worth them all, a new knack as ſome of them call it, that cures (or kills) infalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
               <p>But when I find theſe men have conſiderable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, I cannot but merrily conſider to what that policy drives: perhaps it's hoped that the countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this Phanatick humor of levelling our profeſſion may cauſe it all to be ſpent upon us, and ſave <hi>the Church and State,</hi> on which it's virulency had been ſo long exerciſed, but may it not rather be feared, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will with thoſe very arguments, are now urged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36531:11"/> 
                  <hi>to lay waſt the faculty of Phyſick, and make it a prey to Hoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Coblers and Tinkers, hereafter bring Taylors to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Bar, and Iuglers the Pulpit:</hi> But you will tell me it is eaſy to foretell, that, what hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy done, may poſſibly be done again. But perhaps Sir, it is not ſo eaſie, (if theſe men vvere ever able to bring it into queſtion) to deſtroy the priviledges of a Society of men eſtabliſhed, by ſo many acts of Parliament, and (to ſay nothing of the merit of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their members, whoſe names are celebrated with honour in other Nations) at once to deſtroy the third part of the portions of the younger Sons of the Gentry of England: For to one of the three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, ſome of them are uſually deſigned, nor yet perhaps to rob both our Univerſities, of the honour and advantage, of educating generous, and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous young men, to the faculty of Phyſick, nor of conferring upon them honourable degrees, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of their induſtry and merit: But theſe degrees Sir are our faults, <hi>to be Graduates and Doctors are our crimes,</hi> for otherwiſe we having the advantage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly of more learning, than thoſe that at preſent oppoſe us may have read as many Chymical Authors: Moſt of have been Travellers, and not only ſeen the beſt Elaboratories, but have converſed with, and been Diſciples to the moſt celebrated Chymical Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, our Weſtern part of the world knoweth; we have viſited it's moſt famous Hoſpitals, followed and obſerved the practice of the moſt exerciſed Phyſitians in them, but Sir we are <hi>Doctors,</hi> and <hi>Colledge Doctors</hi> that is after all this, before we could be admitted to the lawful killing of a Cobler in <hi>London,</hi> we have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36531:12"/> been forced, by three days rigid examination, to give Teſtimony that we were able to do it in good form, and according to rule, whereas like a company of Dunces, vve might have ſaved all this charge and trouble, and being but a little while Philoſophers, by the Fire, with the help of a three penny pipkin, and two pence in Charcoſe, we might have found out a true ſeperating medicine, ſhould have killed hundreds, and the tens that had eſcaped, our ſelves nor no body elſe knowing how, ſhould have been printed for cures, we dubbed <hi>Hermetical Doctors,</hi> and have ſet up for the <hi>Chymical Colledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know you will chide me for this, but give me leave to purſue my humour, and laugh at what is ſo truly ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous; I am ſure you can witneſs for me, I am far from being a deſpiſer of Chymiſtry, I love it and own it as one of the beſt keys to the ſecret receſſes of Nature, I think no man worthy the name of a Phyſitian, that is not knowing in it; for it hath not only much mended the Preparations of Medicines, but hath produced many generous Remedies, and of great uſe, but to make every little Fellow, that can build a furnace, burn ſome thing in it until it ſtinks, and then Chriſten it by the name of a great Medicine, a Phyſitian; is to dub a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in the brick-kilns, an Architect; or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of bellows an Organiſt. Would you not, Sir, think that man out of the way, that should commend one for an excellent horſ-man, becauſe he made good Spurs, or a Black-ſmith for an excellent Watch-maker, becauſe he made moſt exquiſite Files, if ſome of theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Chymiſtry only, were by the communication of others, or by chance indeed, Maſters of one or moro
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36531:12"/> good Medicines, would this think you qualifie them for Phyſitians? were it reaſonable that one that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood nothing of the frame or the making of a Watch, should mend it when out of order, although he had all the Tools of a VVatchmaker in his power? I am ſure you would not think it ſo, I wiſh no body elſe would; but it is time I ask your pardon for this digreſſion, and I am ſure of it from you, becauſe you know I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready without prejudice to embrace what ever can reaſonably appear to be for the publick good, and the rendering the facultie of Phyſick truly uſeful and beneficial to Mankind, which muſt give it its greateſt honor; and eſtimation, and of this I hope to give you farther teſtimony as I paſs your propoſitions, and offer ſome of my own; being reſolved (only asking your leave forlittle extravagant digreſſions ſometimes) to anſwer your letter as I read it.</p>
               <p>And therefore muſt next ſay ſomething of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our <hi>Patent,</hi> in which although I do to you acknowledge I was ever of your ſenſe, conſidering the vaſt length of it, in which it was impoſſible, but there muſt be a thouſand clauſes might give occaſion to captious men to quarrel, and ſo of force cauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates for their explanation: Yet I could not but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that ſenſe in my ſelf, when I conſidered the great vvorth, honeſty and known abilities of him that drew up that patent, beſide the great aſſiſtance, and advice he took in the doing of it: I need but name Mr. <hi>John Alleyne</hi> to have vvhat is ſaid of him believed; and Sir you vvere I am ſure ſenſible, in thoſe fevv de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates vve had before <hi>the Committee of the houſe,</hi> what little reaſon there vvas for thoſe ſenſeleſs clamours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36531:13"/> it, how little there vvas asked <hi>de nov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> vve being moſt vvilling to put all our demands into that one of having ſufficient power to put in execution the true intents of Acts already eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>But Sir I think you know how impoſſible almoſt, in a great aſſembly of men it is, to have them all of one mind, nay if they could all agree to the attaining of one end, yet that they ſhould not pitch upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral wayes to it; for in ſuch, ſome men may have no information at all of the thing before them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers extreamly miſinformed, others prejudiced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch men are ingaged in it.</p>
               <p>Sir, if to theſe you had been pleaſed to add the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity of ſome, and the levelling humour of others to oppoſe and deſtroy every thing that lookes like conformity, order or government, you had certainly with thoſe you mentioned, ſaid all the reaſons vvhy any thing ſo long as our Patent, ſhould not eaſily paſs with the conſent of a great aſſembly.</p>
               <p>It is moſt true Sir what you obſerve the genius of this preſent age ſeemes given up to penetrate into the cauſes of natural things, and it ſeemes at laſt to have pitched upon the true meanes, for ſo noble and great an exploration; by promoting uſeful knowledge drawn from experiments, but beſides the famous men you mention for it, <hi>our own nation ought not to have, her Verulam, and Gilbert Forgotten, nor our profeſſion in it Harvey, Gliſten nor Ent;</hi> to mention no others now: and perhaps few men are ſo well qualified, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting this uſeful way of knovvledge, as vvell edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Phyſitians are: I ſhall not novv ſtand to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe hovv much more difficult a thing it is than u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36531:13"/> conſidered to get experience from experiments: how few compare (or are indeed qualified to do it) all circumſtances; and ſince a little one, may make great alterations in things, and the knowledge reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from experience is, that actions, or cauſes ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiated, always will produce ſuch an effect; the circumſtances not conſidered, or taken notice off, vvhat can ſuch an experience amount to. How many impertinent Fooles do we meet with every day, that talk mighty big of experience, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing of it, if they did, theſe vvould neither pretend to miracles themſelves, nor expect them from others, this I confeſs amongſt other things, makes me deſpair of any advantages to be procured, for a real and true promoting the good our profeſſion might bring to mankind, or of any great advantages from the royal Society.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For although certainly, there yet never met a company of more excellent and ingenuous Perſons, who by a moſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and innocent diverſion, are laying the foundation of great good to others, and this by a conſtant and conſiderable charge to themſelves, without the leaſt injury or detriment to any, yet they cannot eſcape the malicious</hi> Scommas and detractations of covetuous Perſons <hi>who either hope from them the Phyloſophers ſtone, or ſome wonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for the getting of mony, or of ignorant and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Curioſos, who would preſently ſee a perpetual motion, or</hi> the ſquaring of the Circle. <hi>Beſide the liberty ſome men take, and think it the only witt too, of turning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, into</hi> Ridicule, <hi>neither</hi> the Scripture, <hi>nor the great author of it</hi> God <hi>himſelfe excepted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, I am now come to that part of your-let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36531:14"/> which indeed ſpeaks your kindneſs to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, you will find few of us ſo brutiſh, as to hate reproofe, or not to love Inſtruction; I hope we all of us covet more the wounds of faithful friend, than the kiſſes of a deceitful enemy, and therefore ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the imperfections, you charge upon the preſent method of practiſing Phyſick in this Nation: The world doth too much want the advantages might be drawn from it, both as to the aſſiſtances to health, and the knowledge of nature in general <hi>our patients lives., and our credits are too often in the power of an ignorant confident Fool; or an idle careleſs Boy:</hi> The charge of it is often inſupportable, as well as uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable, and uncharitable, we many times preſcribe, a drachme of Treacle, worth two pence, to a poor Neighbour out of charity, <hi>the Apothecary</hi> makes him pay half a Crown for <hi>a Cordial Bolus.</hi> There are of us, have retrieved ſome of our preſcriptions, and the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> bills upon them, you will perhaps be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed when I tell you, that where <hi>a Phyſitian</hi> hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Fee, Preſcribed ſome thing worth ſix-pence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was made into twenty four pills, there was ſo many ſhillings paid to <hi>the Apothecarie</hi> upon his bill for it; but I will give you no more accounts of this kinde now, you may in good time ſee ſtore of them, upon profes beyond denial; we have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured already, and will alwayes do what ever lieth in us, to reforme what ever honeſt men think amiſs, or to acquire that perfection knowing men think we yet want, and is attainable, even to an univerſal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, when ever we can be well aſſured it hath been in the World or that it is like ever to be.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36531:14"/>
               <p>We muſt acknowledge too, that the diſtributing two parts of our profeſſion to be exerciſed by others hath been by accident the fatal cauſe of all theſe ills; and though we may ſay, that the vveakneſs of <hi>the heart,</hi> hands, or Eyes of very knowing Phyſitians, might make them vvilling to inſtruct others, to the manual operations in Phyſick, yet perhaps it vvill be hard to believe, that any thing, but the pride and laſineſs of others, <hi>ſpawned Apothecaries;</hi> the diſpenſatories of all the World witneſs, <hi>that Phyſitians made and gave them their Trade:</hi> In <hi>England</hi> their Charter will tell them, <hi>it was our Colledge that made them a Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and you can tell your ſelf Sir how grateful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes they have made us, or will you not rather tell me, how juſtly we are puniſhed for the pride and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs I have confeſt, but if you will a little better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, you may have ſome reaſon to think, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty with the deſign of clear and upright dealing with all men, and a ſuppoſition of improving the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of our profeſſion, were the firſt motives to what was done in this matter: And here Sir give me leave to aſſure you, that you need not ask the pardon of any rational Phyſitian, when you affirme that Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is but a maſs of noble experiments, and I dare with confidence averre, no man can at this time name <hi>one Phyſitian of the Colledge of London,</hi> fond of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles, in the Phyſiologicall part of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and that with old <hi>Doctor Winſton,</hi> and <hi>Doctor VVright,</hi> all our dogmaticall Galleniſtes, as they call them, died, and yet I believe all the inſpired Chymiſts, that labour ſo much at this time for a licenſe (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at laſt to coyn) will never be able with their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36531:15"/> joyned ſtocks, to leave behind them, ſuch an eſtate as the latter did, gotten all by honeſt Gallenical pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
               <p>But Sir to what I was ſaying, there might be great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> motives of honeſty and ingenuity, with proviſion for the ſafety of mankinde, although certainly much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the private intereſt of Phyſitians to make the Pharmacy of Phyſick a perticular Trade, ſuppoſe Sir that goodly Tribe, who have lately with as much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant impudence, as notorious falſhood, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſurpriſe many honourable and noble perſonages, and to perſwade them into a belief, that it was fit to eſtabliſh a Corporation of practiſing Chymiſts, that is a body of men, who ſhall have liberty to exhibit ſecrets of their own; vvhich none can know but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to thoſe that are ſick or would prevent ſickneſs, beſides the miſchiefs that this way, a bold and no way to be controuled ignorance may do; what deſigned murders may not malicious contrivance with merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary knaves perpetrate; that there may be amongſt theſe great pretenders of new diſcoveries in Phyſick, that have been ſuch; mercenary knaves, I mean; I think a man may affirm without danger of an action: But Sir ſince as you have ſaid Phyſick is but a maſs of noble experiments, and thoſe performed by a great variety of medicines, moſt of which have been of known uſe, for the better part of two thouſand years, if a ſelect choice of theſe both ſimple and compound being firſt made, it were committed to a body of men, bred up only to be knowing in the kinds, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe ſimples, and an exact making of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, to have ſuch always in readineſs, to deliver
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36531:15"/> out upon the preſcript of the Phyſitian, and that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript to be kept alwayes on record, by which the goodneſs, and aptneſs in the exhibition might be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged off, when needful; certainly all is done, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally can be thought on, to prevent the miſcheifs, both of ignorance, and villany: Whereas the other way mankind is left without defence againſt, or repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the attaque of either. And certainly Sir, they that firſt deſigned to put the buſineſs of Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, into this way, could not be ignorant of the great profit, and advantage of the other, (that of making their own medicines,) would bring them in, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle practice would ſoon teach the Arts theſe men of mighty Secrets practice: vvhen one that appears mean and poor, gives but ſixpence for that, vvhich better cloaths gives five ſhillings for; beſides, the often ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon occaſion that, vvhich they vvould otherwiſe hire ſome body to throw out of doors; beſide, that knowing men might often coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the people, with advantage to them, as well as credit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and here give me leave to tell you a ſhort ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>A Phyſitian of your acquaintance and mine, in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in the beginning of his practice there; being ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly carryed to a Gentlevvoman, that had been for ſome time ſick of a feavour; and ſhe living at ſome diſtance, from his place of aboad; or from any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, found as ſoon as ever he came, that though ſhe appeared juſt then worſe than in the vvhole pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent time of her ſickneſs, and conſequently deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of by her friends, yet that her ſickneſs vvas very neer determining, and as he thought he had reaſon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36531:16"/> to believe to health, he vvas unwilling in his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in a family of great relations in the Countrey, to loſe the credit of a great cure, and therefore thought it neceſſary to ſeem to do ſome thing in it, yet ſomething that might not at all impede, vvhat na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vvas ſo vvell in doing, and vvhich he did believe, before he could ſend home or to <hi>an Apothecaries,</hi> ſhe vvould have done vvithout him: vvhileſt he vvas conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering this he had at a Table vvhere he vvas leaning, made up three or four fine pills, of white bread, and conveying them into a little box in his pocket, by and by calls for a ſpoon, and in ſome liquor, vvith due formality gave them, giving direction for her careful attendance, with confident aſſurance of her ſpeedy recovery, which accordingly happened, for in very few houres, ſhe fell into a moſt profuſe ſweat, and ſoon recovered perfectly: the Gentleman was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly famous for his great cure, but his greater cordial, and forced indeed to make a good one up into that form, to ſatisfie the importunity of his patients for it, you may ſee by this Sir, how eaſie it is for any one, to whom ſome lucky chance hath given credit, if he will but pretend to ſecrets, of ſecret, and perticular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, to impoſe upon the not conſidering part of the World, who yet are ſo zealous to be thought knowing, they are alwayes finding out, and rendring the cauſes of things, and generally vvill have that to be it, vvhich is the next obvious to their ſhort under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, though fartheſt of any removed from the nature of that thing, they apply it to: And Sir, you may by the by obſerve too, how often it muſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in like caſes, that bold and ignorant Quackes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36531:16"/> deſtroy thoſe, vvhom nature vvould cure, vvhileſt the knowing and experienced Phyſitian, who hath been long ſince taught, vvhere truly there is need of it, to fly to the aſſiſtance of remedies, as extream as the danger, vvill not by unneceſſary, and ignorant tamperings deſtroy, vvhere nature vvould certainly cure.</p>
               <p>But novv Sir, give me leave to aſſure you, that thoſe tvvo great evills, vvhich the vvay of practie as you ſuppoſe it novv to be, had produced, have been of late years very much amended amongſt us, for ſince the time that <hi>our great Dootor Harvey</hi> acquired that honour to himſelf, and to our nation in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Anatomical diſcoveries our younger Phyſitians grew generouſly to emulate both his fortune, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and perhaps the World hath not a Society, of our profeſſion, in which conſidering the number of them, there are ſo many excellent Anatomiſts, nor did they ſo give themſelves up to this, that they neglected the enquirlng into the natures of vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and minerals, they had, and have ſtill though I acknowledge not by any publick order of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their committees and meetings for perticular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries, thoſe that are our old men now thus ſpent their younger years, and I think the learned Authors of them will own, that the treatiſes <hi>de Rachitide, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomia hepatis,</hi> and <hi>de Glandulis</hi> had, if not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, yet improvement from ſuch meetings as theſe; and he that hath lately heard <hi>Sir George Ents anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Exerciſes</hi> muſt have acknowledged the great progreſs that is made in the <hi>Anatomia comparata,</hi> and give me leave to tell you Sir, men that have been acquainted with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36531:17"/> the practice of our Engliſh Phyſitians, muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no age yet ever ſaw ſuch an improvement of the <hi>materia medica;</hi> Sir they muſt be very malicious, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that have the face to affirm, that we are ſo tyed up to the preſcriptions of <hi>Galen,</hi> as not to have embraced and cultivated Chymiſtry, and that with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, reaſon, and ſucceſs, we have not indeed embraced the lying and boaſting part of it, to cry up our ſelves, and medicines, at ſuch a rate; that if the boaſted virtues of any one of them were true, there were no need of any other Phyſitian, or medicine, and the ſtupidity of the World, or of thoſe that poſſeſs ſuch wonder working medicines, were to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the one ſhould ever want health, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mony; I will not undertake Sir, to juſtify every compoſition, in our preſent diſpenſatory, though I dare affirm there are as good, if not better in it, as to the reaſon of the compoſitions, and the uſefulneſs of them, than in any other publick one now extant; beſides that all of them have been approved by a long experience. I mean ſuch an one as knows how to make uſe of them with conſideration of all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, thoſe little Phanatick heads, that pretend to find fault with quantities, or the wayes of compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, in preſcribed, and approved Medicines. (I do not intend by this to juſtifie ſome defects, in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and rules of compounding, or the miſtakes of juſt proportions, to make things ſuch as they ſhould be,) do not know what ſomewhere in your letter you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, from our great <hi>Verulam,</hi> how little the nature of any thing is known to us <hi>a priori,</hi> and that in things of experience, a little alteration from the way
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36531:17"/> experienced, makes it an other thing, and puts us to ſeek a new; I do aſſure you Sir, knowingly that <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elfon</hi> who being bred <hi>an Apothecary,</hi> hath made a rational attempt, to the correcting <hi>the Auguſtan Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatory,</hi> hath ſpoiled ſome very good medicines, and even in matter of fact is ſo much miſtaken, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that in ſome diſtillations nothing of that can be brought over the Helm, which if he had ever tryed he muſt have known the contrary, and ſo in ſome other things propoſeth the doing of what I think, cannot be done, in that way he propoſeth.</p>
               <p>I do aſſure you Sir, our little Juntoes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, meet not to drink, or to talke onely, but they do impoſe taskes upon each other, and work chearfully and willingly in all the parts of Phyſick, ſo that I hope hereafter throughly to ſatisfie you, that we have in this laſt age ſet our ſelves to improve our profeſſion, by thoſe that you approve to be, and are certainly the beſt wayes to do it, and you will find, <hi>that when ever we come to the reſolutions of making our own medicines altogether: or have our priviledges ſo bettered and confirmed that we may ſafely truſt</hi> the Apothecary, <hi>that their is proviſion for</hi> a diſpenſatory, <hi>conſiſting of ſo choyce experimented medicines, both Chymical and others,</hi> eſpecially with relation to our own nation, <hi>that no age hath yet produced a better, and they ſhall be all ſuch too, as the Phyſitians of our Colledge have made, and long experimentea themſelves.</hi> But I think as the caſe ſtands yet <hi>betwixt us and the Apothecaries,</hi> none will expect, we ſhould put any thing of ſuch a nature into their hands, who have made us ſo kind returnes for what we entruſted them with before: But Sir, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36531:18"/> you may know this is not onely talk, I will give you now ſome little account of a weekly <hi>Junto</hi> that as I am informed have met conſtantly this nine or ten years, never increaſing their number above five, and of which I think it a misfortune not to be one: for ſome years it was their buſineſs to examine as far as they could, all the diſpenſatories they could get, with the reformations and animadverſions upon them, to compare divers compoſitions with our own, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider upon what authority they had been received, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered or amended, and to enquire, as much as the nature of the thing would bear, into the reaſon of the compoſitions; for though we be aſſured of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a medicine, perhaps the why and the how ſuch effect is produced, will not be ſo eaſily aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and in compoſitions that which ſome little buſie body, to appear wiſe, will be making preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to mend, by altering, may be that which gives it as to this particular effect, its greateſt Energy: He that conſiders what alterations ſome bodies produce in others, though at diſtance, vvhich yet a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of poſition, or change of the Medium may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vvill be apt enough to apprehend, how little a thing may alter the reſult of a compoſition, vvhere divers things muſt be preciſely, as to the meaſures of proportion, and time, and the quality of <hi>the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums,</hi> by vvhich they are to be imbodied, ſo made up; to produce ſuch effects, and though every novice in Chimiſtry may know this, yet vvanting the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of other things to enable them prudently to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and adjouſt things to determine effects, or at leaſt to the way of knowing truly their effects: it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36531:18"/> ſerves them rather to ſpoil, than mend any thing they take in hand: <hi>This little Committee</hi> therefore I was ſpeaking of, made it their buſineſs moſt to enquire into the real effects of medicines, and into all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that attend the effects produced, and to this end did not onely bring in, and communicate to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, diligent obſervations in their own practice, but as much as they could, that two of the moſt eminent Phyſitians in the Town, by looking over their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts, and diligently enquiring into the occaſions and ſucceſs of them, they had their times too, not only of conſidering home-bred, and exotick ſimples, as to the outward appearance of their ſeveral ſpecies; but of their natures and effects, when uſed alone. And here Sir, I cannot but tell you, I do believe there are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few Phyſitians of this preſent Colledge that would be long to ſeek in any place of the World, for ſome proper helps in any occaſion of ſickneſs they ſhould be called too, though there were no <hi>Apothecaries</hi> or <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> beſides himſelf in the whole Countrey. But beſides this Sir, this little <hi>Junto</hi> too in other years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, brought in not only the Hiſtories of the diſeaſes their own practice furniſhed them with, but any remarkeable ones they could be furniſhed with from others, as well as many from books, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the enquiring into the natures of them, both upon old and new principles, they conſidered the juſt circumſtances, and meaſures of applying the moſt effectual remedies to their cure: In other years, they treated one another once a week, with <hi>ſome animal, for anatomical diſſections,</hi> and very rarely in that whole time met, but they had ſome thing relating to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36531:19"/> to enquire into: But I hope by that time you come to Town, to give you a better account of this, and to make you and my ſelf too, better acquainted with ſome of this induſtrious meetings and I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you this account now, only to let you know, that we are not thoſe uſeleſs inſipid drones, that ſome things of great noiſe would render us to the World; I could tell you too of greater things done, for theſe will own themſelves as yet but for ſeekers by ſome of greater eminency, and of the elaboratories, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity every day exerciſed in aſſiſting of the poorer ſort, but they are no <hi>Groomes of the great Chamber</hi> that do it, nor will they bribe any body, with the hopes, or promiſe of a charity, to preach their cures, and their bounty, and to aſſert the truth of things, of which it is impoſſible they ſhould have any knowledge; yet I would not have you think, I am now juſtifying eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual member of our Society, in every thing. We are not perhaps all prudent, or good natured men; but I dare all their enemies, to charge any one of them with want of learning in his profeſſion, with the want of honeſty in the exerciſe of it, or in his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in relation to others, becauſe I am ſure if there be any ſuch amongſt us, it is becauſe they are not made appear to be ſuch; and I know the conſtitutions of our particular government ſo well, it would ſoon free it ſelf from ſuch ſcandals as that, and it is ſomething of this in our Government, that will alwayes make ignorant, or vitious perſons fly, as much as they can or dare, in our faces, for we do not only make an on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the learning, and ſufficiencie for practice, of thoſe that are admitted of our body, but into their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36531:19"/> probitie and good manners too, which that vve may have time to do, no man can be admitted ſooner than three moneths, after his firſt making his deſire of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion known to the Colledge, that in the mean time the preſent Fellowes may have time to enquire after him, and if there be juſt exceptions againſt his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or his honeſty, they may be objected before his admiſſion, as <hi>Candidate,</hi> after which to, if he doth not behave himſelf as a learned, and an honeſt Phyſitian, he ſhall then be barred for ever being Fellow; and there are examples of Fellowes being expelled, and forfeiting all their priviledges amongſt us, for ill pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, diſhoneſt Mountebankery, and ill manners: And this I take it Sir, is bidding open war to ignorance, and knavery, and therefore vve muſt expect the effects of it; all the miſchiefs, ſuch enemies can do us: for no vertuous or learned perſon, vvill ever ſcruple to have his name regiſtred, and enjoy priviledges, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eſtabliſhed by lavv, amongſt a company of men of known learning, and of no blaſted credits; becauſe they are required, with all reſpect and civility imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to give an honourable, and honeſt teſtimonie of their abilities in their profeſſion, to men too, vvho have given the greateſt teſtimonies, of any Societies of men in the World, that they are not tyed up to the dictates of any Sect of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> or <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> they have long ſince embraced the more generous, and uſeful way of Philoſophiſing freely; they cheriſh it, and encourage it in all their members, and I do aſſure you Sir, no man was ever diſcouraged by them, who gave a good account that he had judgment, and abilities for the practice of Phyſick, though he vvere deficieat
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36531:20"/> in the abſtruſer notions, and nice diſtinctions of the Schooles, provided they had no reaſon to think him other, than an honeſt man: therefore certainly thoſe that know this, muſt always think <hi>the cry againſt Doctors, and Colledg, is but a compact of ignorance and knavery,</hi> which, if I do not forget before I have ended my let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I will make you a little more ſenſible of, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you a ſhort account of thoſe people that make it moſt.</p>
               <p>But I hope you are by this time ſatisfied, that the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Phyſitians,</hi> have without a Monitor, put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ways of improving the uſefulneſs of their profeſſion, as much as the nature of the thing is capable of, and nothing but ignorance, or malice can deny, what you are pleaſed to take notice of; viz. <hi>That this Colledg of Phyſitians in</hi> London, <hi>hath more advanced the true knowledg of Phyſick, within this laſt forty years, than any one Society of Phyſitians in</hi> Europe <hi>beſides;</hi> and then if you pleaſe to conſider, that this hath been for the moſt part carried on, by the private endeavours of ſeveral members of it, our Colledg having none of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of publique Profeſſors, competently endowed from the Publique, for teaching in the ſeveral parts of Medicine (onely one endowed Lecture from a private Benefactor for Anatomy,) nor no publique Phyſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden, nor Elaboratories for Chymical operations, except thoſe of private erection. You may perhaps be induced to believe, that thoſe men, who have been ſo induſtrious without thoſe helps, might advance much farther with them. If the Phyſitians of thoſe Hoſpitals we have, had ſuch a Salary, as might oblige them to attend thoſe places diligently, and to ſuffer our younger
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36531:20"/> Phyſitians for ſome time to attend on them; by their direction to ſerve, and miniſter diligently about the ſick, keeping exact accounts of all Accidents, Cures and miſcarriages, and of the Anatomie of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid bodies that die, and ſuch of thoſe as appeared re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally uſeful, to be regiſtred in the Archives of our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, might we not hope in ſome time, to arrive at as much perfection in our Art, as is to be hoped for, conſidering that we muſt, I fear when all is done, be ſtill mortal, and whilſt men are ſo unwilling to believe that, or at leaſt that it ſhould be ſo yet with them, how infirm or old ſoever they be; there will be imployment for bold pretending ignorance, which ſhall too, thruſt ſober knowledg out of doors; for where thoſe daſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fears of dying are, they will catch hold of the next log that offers it ſelf to their ſhort and fearful apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; though in the bottom of ignorance, where they muſt inevitably periſh by it, certainly that <hi>Bishop,</hi> had a great and generous ſoul, not clogged with thoſe miſbecoming fears, who upon a bold undertaking of a <hi>Mountebank</hi> to cure him, when his Phyſitians deſpaired, choſe rather to dye in the hands of Art, as more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the courage of a man, and the ſobriety of a Chriſtian, who ſhould uſe none but lawful means to preſerve himſelf, than to have it ſaid when he was gone, that he would have been beholding to baſe and ſordid Ignorance, for a few more years of pain and trouble.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, I was juſt coming to the Reformation you propoſe in the practice of Phyſick, if I were not ſtartled at the danger you are running your ſelf into, it is well ſince your Letter is publick, that your name is concealed, what do you think otherwiſe might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36531:21"/> of you and it, that dare venture to provoke the mighty men of fire, what? <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and <hi>Helmont</hi> not <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> I ſee ſquadrons arming againſt you, the Roſters of <hi>Geber,</hi> the Toſters of <hi>Lully,</hi> the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſeers of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and the <hi>Olla Podrida men of Helmont,</hi> men that all know how to roſt Apples, ſtew Prunes, toſt Cheeſe; and ſome who can, it is believed for need, toſs a Panacke, can ſay, <hi>Archeus, Cas, Blas, Duelech, Duumvirate,</hi> and a thouſand harder words, which though you do not, they all underſtand, one as well as t'other, and becauſe you do not underſtand them at all, and perhaps may think, you have a pretty moral aſſurance they cannot, becauſe they are unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible; will you call the <hi>Philoſophy of Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Helmont, idle and extravagant Theories?</hi> I dare aſſure you, I can tell you a way, how you ſhall come to think you underſtand all thoſe wonderful things, as well as they, that think they underſtand them beſt, for there are ſome that know the emptineſs of them as well as you, but uſe them for ſounds ſake, and to amuſe admiring ignorance: but the way in ſhort for you, or any body to underſtand them as well as any, is to be mad, as they that think they do underſtand them: do you not remember the two Fellowes of a <hi>Colledge in Cambridge</hi> that had been for ſome years mad, and at laſt growing a little civiller in their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, were ſuffered to walk abroad, and coming into the Chappel at Evening Prayer, ſat devoutly and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively there, until the ſecond leſſon vvas now to be read, when one of them, before he vvhoſe turn it vvas to read, could get to the desk vvas there, had turned to the proper Leſſon and began to read; all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36531:21"/> were a little ſurprized, but perceiving he read diſtinctly and orderly, they let him go on to the end; hopeing he would as orderly then recede; but inſtead of that, he began a very mad, ſenſeleſs comment upon the Chapter he had read; ſome were quickly ordered to get him out of the Chappel, whileſt the reſt began the <hi>nunc dimiitis,</hi> when Prayer was done, the other madman, who had continued civill to the end of prayers, coming to the maſter, deſired to know, why his fellovv mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was not ſuffered to go on, with his pious and learned Comment, and being anſwered, <hi>becauſe he talked like a Fool, and a Mad-man, what none could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;</hi> replyed with ſome admiration, <hi>How, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him, I profeſs,</hi> Sir, <hi>I underſtood him very well;</hi> and certainly it is much after the ſame manner, that theſe Men of mighty words, and inextricable notions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand one another; but I cannot forbear to obſerve, a pretty kind of errant like humour, dictated perhaps from the <hi>Cuſtos errans,</hi> in theſe mens underſtandings, that what ever there is plain, and of good uſe to be found, in theſe Authors they deal on, they either do not underſtand, over-ſee, or elſe paſs by, as diſdaining to take notice of any thing leſs then Wind-Mills; but by this time you are, I believe, laughing at me, who have run ſo goodly a courſe at them my ſelf, and therefore I come now to the reformation you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>And do aſſure you Sir, for all the ſixteen reaſons you give, I ſhall my ſelf be moſt willing ſo ſubmit, to that very reformation, if we cannot have a better, but ſince you do your ſelf intimate a better, from the primitive and certainly for that reaſon, that they made
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36531:22"/> their own medicines, the beſt practice of Phyſick; why ſhould <hi>the Colledge of Phyſitians</hi> go on to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage a Trade, ſet up only for their eaſe, and which if they will themſelves be induſtrious, there is not at all any uſe of to mankinde; why ſhould we be concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their being a Corporation, or having been bred to a Trade, which hath onely given them the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, before they vvell underſtand that, to invade a profeſſion, that few of them can ever be capable of underſtanding; ſome of them have given it for reaſon why they did oppoſe the paſſing of our patent, that it would hinder them from practiſing Phyſick, which they did and ought to do, and ſhall they ſay and do this expreſly againſt known Lawes, and ſhall vve ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to do vvhat both the Laws allovv, our patients ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, our own credits, and intereſts calls upon us to do, that is, make all our own medicines; eſpecially at this time, when we are ready to make a good and thorough reformation in the whole <hi>Materia meaica,</hi> and when perhaps, we ſhall not find many of them, for the general want amongſt them of knowledge, in Chymical operations, capable of aſſiſting us: I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you Sir, there are a great many amongſt us, I am ſure ſome of your acquaintance very knowing not only in all our home bred ſimples, but in the ways of knowing and chuſing the beſt and moſt uſeful exotick medicinal things, (thoſe that are not, let them in Gods name learn, of thoſe are) and therefore I cannot ſee if we will ſet our ſelves throughly, and induſtriouſly to our buſineſs, what need we can have <hi>of Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> eonſidering how many very good <hi>Druggiſts</hi> there are in Town, and then having nothing to do: with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36531:22"/> 
                  <hi>Apothecaries</hi> at all, we comply wholly with your firſt reaſon, we obtain all the advantages of your ſecond, third and fourth, for indeed as you well obſerve in this, what advantage in nature can an ignorant <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanke, or boaſting pretender to Chymiſtry</hi> have, beyond <hi>a ſober rational Phyſitian,</hi> but in that of making trivial, and common things great ſecrets, the better to cheate a ſort of people, that love to be cheated; and were born only to admire noiſe, and emptineſs: This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſecrets Sir, like the Quakers light within them, is to be encountered by no reaſon, he that is the moſt knowing in all the <hi>materia medica,</hi> and the moſt skilful in the preparations of medicines, will find it perhaps a hard thing, to confute a fellow that with confidence tells you, of a thing of his own invention, unknown to others, or of a particular way of preparing a known medicine, invented by himſelf, though how many of that kinde, when they have been known, have proved, (if of uſe or good at all,) ſuch as were known to every body, and of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practice in the Town, and yet how many do we ſee every day, who if a fellow, nay <hi>any old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> whoſe education hath been never ſo remote from the thing they pretend to, or their parts never ſo mean, ſhall confidently tell them of great ſecrets, they preſently cry thoſe up, for the only knowing perſons, and all men elſe as <hi>Sots and Ideots,</hi> never conſidering that if a fellow ignorant in every thing elſe, even vvanting much to have a ſhare in common ſenſe, ſhould by hap ſtumble upon any thing that is very good, and prove able to make up a good medicine cuſtome, and uſage, yet by it is impoſſible but that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36531:23"/> his paramount ignorantce, ſhould ſome times do great miſchiefs vvith this good medicine; for we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch a thing as this, to be of force to cauſe great alterations in our bodies, and then it may if not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vvith reaſon, make thoſe alterations ſometimes to our deſtruction, except it be an Univerſal medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine; and then I aſſure you, I ſhall no more plead for the faculty of Phyſick, but vvill burn all my books, and if I cannot acquire it my ſelf, vvill vvith all my heart ſerve that earthly God, that I ſhall know Maſter of it; but till then Sir, I cannot but think it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that Phyſitians ſhould be Maſters of thoſe things they have been the inventers of themſelves, and ſince thoſe they have entruſted to make them refuſe all ſubordination to them, or to ſubmit medicines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and deſigned by Phyſitians, for ſuch and ſuch uſes, to their judgments, whether they be fit for theſe uſes or not, nay rather then miſs the ſerving of a bill ſent to them, becauſe they want the things preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, vvill according to their ſhallow capacities, put in one thing for an other, or any thing, no matter vvhat, ſo they be paid for the bill, though to the loſs of the Phyſitians credit, and health, if not life of the patient. I cannot Sir, but think it moſt neceſſary, as well as moſt reaſonable; <hi>that Phyſitians reſume this part of Phyſick into their own hands wholly: and either make Medicines for their own practice themſelves, or keep, ſome in their houſes, who may do it under their eye, and ſo enable them, to give a better account of all they do; to the world, their own conſciences, and to God.</hi> But if you urge againſt me what I have ſaid before for the making the Pharmacy of Phyſick a particular Trade, as argument ſtill to continue it ſoe, I ſhall quickly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36531:23"/> reply, I will not be againſt it, ſo that it be reduced to its primitive conſtitution, and that vve be ſecured of their honeſt and faithful diſpenſing of our preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they have their ſhops ſtored, vvith good and vvholeſome medicines, and to ſecure that, that they of all men ſhall not on any termes be ſuffered to practiſe, for that deſtroies the very reaſon of their conſtitution; and this indeed is the great ſecret, and ſtirrs up their induſtrious oppoſition to us, for whileſt they can vend medicines, by their own practice, without the ſurvey or preſcript of the Phyſtian, the putting off the worſt, and refuſe things, brings in the greateſt gain. Beſides, that not knowing, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering more than that gain, they never want any thing: that which comes next to hand makes up any Phyſitians preſcript, and <hi>powder of a rotten poſt, may with ſome wonderful commendations of its excellency, and virtue, ſerve there own practice, better than the</hi> beſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled ſpices: And that this is too much truth, I think is evident by their no oppoſition, when lately the pretended Chymiſts ſo induſtriouſly laboured the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelves a Corporation; for in that the knife was at their Throats, &amp; <hi>Apothecaries</hi> vvhen that is done, will certainly in a little time ſignifie nothing: All the hurt it can do <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> is to force them to what I would have them now do, the <hi>making their one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines,</hi> and truly I think a very little conſideration may ſerve a man to forſee, that the next age will ſcarce know, what <hi>an Apothecarie</hi> is; for vvhat vvith theſe pretenders to ſecrets, and the affronts the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries</hi> put upon us, with their confident inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our profeſſion, we ſhall be driven at laſt, to what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36531:24"/> I have been thus long ſpeaking for: Our old practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are unvvilling yet to come to it, but the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger provide for it a pace, and I doubt not but vvill finde encouragement enough to perſue it: but the deſign of your fifth reaſon, for the better breeding up of yound Students in our faculty, will hardly ever be vvell acquired, as to the curing of diſeaſes, but by ſome ſuch conſtitution for the <hi>Phyſitians of our Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals,</hi> as I have formerly intimated: for although e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Doctor in Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſick ſhould be able to teach the <hi>Anatomical, Botanical,</hi> and <hi>Pharmacutical</hi> knowledge of our profeſſion, yet there are not many that have ſo much practice in great Citties as to need help; beſides that thoſe that are able to ſend for <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> will not alwayes be contented that a younger <hi>Phyſitian</hi> ſhould be truſted vvith the knowledge of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. I could urge a great many inconveniences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this vvay, but there can be none againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting our Hoſpitalls ſo, that the ſick in them might be much better attended, and our younger <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> In a few Years, acquire great knowledge, in the practicall part of their profeſſion, for thus a three, or four Years attendance, on perſons of all ages, and ſexes, and ſick of all, perhaps of more than all the now known diſeaſes, and under a vvell experienced practitioner, muſt give men of any capacity, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if before but reaſonably vvell grounded, in the true principles of their profeſſion, that judgment, (if you vvill give me leave to uſe one hard vvord) <hi>that Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſme, in judging the nature, and cauſes of diſeaſes, and application of fit remedies to the cures of them, which only indeed makes an able and a fortunate Phyſitian</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36531:24"/> vvithout vvhich all the ſecrets and vvonderful receipts, <hi>the promiſing Quacks of this age boaſt off,</hi> ſignifie not ſo well as <hi>herb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn in Porredge,</hi> ſince they are ſo far from doing no hurt, that they many times, do fatall and irreparable miſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſs, by an unſeaſonable, and ignorant application of them.</p>
               <p>But certainly part of your ſixth reaſon is grounded upon miſtake, if you reckon that the <hi>Fees of Phyſitians</hi> makes any very conſiderable advance, in the charge of taking Phyſick; For as no ingenuous Phyſitian can or will grate on the neceſſitous condition of his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and make a Cure more irkſome to him than a diſeaſe, ſo t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e conſtitutions of our Society, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom as prevalent as a Law, forbid, and reſtrain the moſt covetous amongſt us, to contract for Cures, or to make any bargains for our rewards, <hi>I ſpeak now for the Fellows and Candidates of our Society:</hi> And what ever <hi>VVeſtminſter-Hall</hi> may ſhew done by others, I am very confident it can produce very few Suites commenced by any of that number, againſt thoſe that have recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſickneſs: The truth of it is, we are generally, too much at the mercy of our Patients, as to that. An honeſt, and conſcientious Phyſitian (I am ſure if we are not all ſuch, we ought to be ſuch) cannot neglect the life of a man, committed to his care, but many of us can affirm by experience enough, that there are too many, that very much undervalue, not only their Phyſitians, who by Gods bleſſing on his skill, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, hath reſtored them health for ſickneſs, and caſe for pain, but even that health and eaſe, they are now poſſeſſed of, whilſt (though well able to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) they give mean, and dirty rewards to their Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36531:25"/> or perhaps reproaches inſtead of any. <hi>It is a common excuſe for their cloſeneſs of hand, that the Doctor gets his Fees eaſily enough, which he only makes a viſit and writes a few words for,</hi> but <hi>not to wiſh them that ſollicitude of mind and anguish of ſoul, that the doubtful condition of a Patient hath given me,</hi> I wiſh they would conſider for others, what I am ſure they would for themſelves, that is the real loſs, and gain in all they deal for; they would then eaſily compute, that beſides the labour of ſtudie, and the expence of as much time, as would make up two Apprentiſhips, before a man can acquire a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful title to Phyſick; the charge of his Education, the taking Degrees, moſt commonly too his Travel, the making of Experiments, and his Library, may amount to a greater ſtock, than is neceſſary to make a man a Maſter in any other profeſſion whatſoever; and yet there are farr greater encouragments for other profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions than for ours, the two other learned ones of Law and Divinity, mount men to the higheſt Honors and Authorities next the King, and Royal Family, <hi>wealthy Revenues are provided for Churchmen, and places of great profit for men of the Law; but a Doctor of Phyſick never gets farther;</hi> ſome few of them acquire the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being more immediately in the ſervice of the King, but I have not heard of any of them amonſt us, very rich, except Sir <hi>Theodore Mayerne;</hi> all which I have ſaid to inſinuate, what I doubt not but you will eaſily acknowledg; that as Phyſitians may very well deſerve the Fees, that uſe and cuſtome hath allowed them, ſo it is not by thoſe Fees that the charge of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is increaſed, beyond what people are willing to make it; ſince every Patient is in this caſe his own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36531:25"/> Chancellor. To confirm this truth to you, before I come to diſcover the little arts by which the charge of Phyſick is really encreaſed; Let me tell you a Story, which to me ſeems not very unpleaſant.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>One of our number, and a friend of yours and mine, one day in his ſtudy was addreſſed to, by a man that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but of an ordinary condition, with his urinal in hand, deſiring as he phraſed it, his worſhips advice, upon due conſideration of his complaints, if proved the man had gotten a diſeaſe, that too often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to his betters, and being now of ſome moneths ſtanding, required a little more than ordinary care to root it out; he ſaid enough to make the Phyſitian commiſerate his caſe, who without any conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his promiſes of being very thankful, gave him directions then without a Fee, and ſo from time to time after for his cure; ſo that in about two months time, with ſix or ſeven pounds charge to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, (who was wiſe enough to be paid for his Phyſick as the patient had it) the man thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf perfectly cured, but in this time the Phyſitian had learned, that he was a fellow did pay for his debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and was able enough to pay for his cure too, and ſo grew into ſome expectation of the fellows pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, who one day coming to him, told him he was come to give his worſhips content, the Phyſitian ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly adviſed him to be ſure he were well, becauſe in this diſeaſe men too often thought themſelves well too ſoon, ſince it was in humane bodies like horſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh in the ground, where if the leaſt <hi>Fibre</hi> of the roots be left, it will over run the ground again; but he boaſting of good ſtomach, freedom from paines,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36531:26"/> and cleanneſs of skin, very generouſly laid down two half Crowns for the Phyſitians reward, vvho diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meaneſs of it, told him if he vvere able to give no more, he vvould not take that from him, adding that if he had gone to ſome of thoſe, that uſe to make bargaines, they would have made him pay twenty pounds for his cure, beſides his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; to which the fellow replied with a little emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how Sir, twenty pound, I proteſt I vvould not take ſo much Phyſick again, if you vvould give me forty ſhillings, and ſo vvith his tvvo half Crovvns in his hand, left the Phyſitian, vvho heard no more of him, nor did he I aſſure you ever think of ſuing him. I doubt not but many of our profeſſion, often meet with ſuch returnes as theſe, and if we did not meet with more generous, and worthy dealing from better perſons, the practice of Phyſick would be forſaken by all learned, and ingenious perſons. And the world would want that improvement of real knowledge which that faculty hath, and doth every day make.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But as I inſinuated before, this Story was only brought in to advertiſe you, that whilſt all men are their own Chancellours as to the reward they give their Phyſitians, thoſe rewards are perhaps, the leaſt part of the charge in taking Phyſick, and yet it muſt be acknowledged, as you obſerve, that the charge of Phyſick is ſometimes intollerable, and unconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I will endeavour now to let you ſee how indeed it too often comes to be ſo.</p>
               <p>And that you may know I am not partial to our ſelves, I will acknowledge that I fear <hi>Phyſitians</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36531:26"/> contribute to the making this charge, <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> very often, but patients are for the moſt part the occaſion of it themſelves: few amongſt us are ſo wiſe as the <hi>Romans,</hi> who entertaining, or being entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſome <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with more Wine than men of that Nation uſe to drink, was the next morning very ſick, with all thoſe accidents that accompany the debauches of men not uſed to it; he ſent preſently for his Phyſitian, a learned and ingenious perſon of our Nation, one who lived long in <hi>Rome,</hi> and from whom I had the Story, who finding what his ſickneſs was, by making him keep his bed that day, with a little broth only, found him the next morning reaſonably well recovered, but ſtill in fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r that ſo violent a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as he had felt the day before, would not go off ſo eaſily, and therefore prayed another viſit from his Phyſitian in the afternoon, who then found him up, and almoſt in the opinion he ſhould be well; which his Phyſitian wholly confirmed him in: the man with great joy vvhen the Phyſitian vvas going, <hi>puts two Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines of Gold into his hand,</hi> at which he being a little ſurprized, ſuch fees by men of his quality not being uſually given there, <hi>nay my Doctor ſaith the patient, when you cure me without putting thoſe Devills of Senna, Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbe, Agaricke, Marobatanes, into my Belly, I will pay you five times better, than when you torment me with all or any of them;</hi> but few amongſt us, will think a Phyſitian deſerves a reward if he orders them no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, not conſidering that he that conducts a ſick man ſooneſt, ſafeſt and vvith leaſt trouble, to that health he vvants, deſerves better than he that by unpleaſant, long, and troubleſome vvaies brings him to it: It is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36531:27"/> of <hi>an Engliſh man the Story is told, who gave the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor a ſhilling, ana his Wife ſix pence, who helped in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him about the roome by his tooth, and not drawing it: but thought the tooth-drawer did not deſerve ſix pence, who pulled it out dexterouſly and quickly, becauſe he had taken no more paines in the doing it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This humour too often inclines <hi>the Phyſitian,</hi> when perhaps there is little need of it, to charge <hi>the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients</hi> belly vvith Phyſick, and his Table vvith pots, and glaſſes; but if <hi>the Apothecary</hi> be a friend to the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> called in by him, if he doth not then ſerve the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> as much as the patient, 'tis ten to one but he is turned out again, however will ſcarce ever be called another time: And it ſeems to me Sir, that I am now upon the very reaſon of the great charge you mention in taking Phyſick, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there are fevv Tradeſ-men, that think it a fault to ſell as much of that commodity they Trade in, and to as much profit as they can, I am ſure the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as much as they can, to thoſe will buy it, can never be thought one; yet few people mark, that it is as much the intereſt of <hi>the Apothecary</hi> to do this, as it is of any other Tradeſ-man. When an <hi>Apothecary</hi> calls to ſee how <hi>my Lord or his worſhip, or my Lady and the family are, as to health,</hi> he is a very diligent, honeſt, careful, good natured man; at that time <hi>the daughter Betty, or the ſon Thomas, looke as they had the vvormes, or they did not eat their Supper with any Stomach laſt night</hi> (perhaps by reaſon of two full a Dinner at noon) <hi>or the VVoman or the Maid have a pain in their Heads, it may be by ſitting up late when the Maſter and Lady were in Bed, but the Apothecary will ſend ſomething that is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36531:27"/> good for them, preſently that Doctor ſuch a one preſcribed,</hi> (for uſually it is upon the authority of ſome Phyſitian, and with pretence to his Medicines they drive on this trade) and the Child or the Woman is well, and all is well at that time; but ſometimes it happens, that by the untimely exhibition of a very good remedy, they grow ſick indeed, and until the <hi>Apothecary</hi> is frighted with eminent danger, his trade drives on as he could vviſh it; but if any danger appear, a <hi>Phyſitian</hi> muſt be called, and the <hi>Apothecary</hi> muſt be adviſed with who is fitteſt to be called; and methinks it ſeems very natural, that he ſhould call in ſuch an one, if he knows him, that is moſt likely to ſave his credit, and vvill beſt help to carry on the trade of ſelling his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; ſuch a one, who if he come Three or Four times a day, writes new Bills for the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> compound <hi>Glyſters, rich cordial Juleps and Boluſes, Pearl, Beſoar</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> words that ſignifie very much in aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the ſumm, at the foot of the Account in an <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Bill: I do aſſure you many of us in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies vvhere vve are <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in ordinary, have known the <hi>Apotheoaries Bill at Chriſtmas</hi> come to thirty, Forty, Fifty pounds, ſometimes more, for Phyſick for the Family, vvhen no Phyſitian hath ordained Ten pounds vvorth of Phyſick; for in ſuch Families the <hi>Coachman, Groom and Footman upon any little occaſion will be helping the Apothecary of the Family off with his ware, without troubling Mr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>octor for his advice, whether it be proper or no;</hi> and Sir, if to theſe arts you add the unconſcionable priſes of ſome of them (for I do not in this, nor in any thing before charge all of that profeſſion, I know divers honeſt knowing and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36531:28"/> Men amongſt them) put upon things of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, you may eaſily compute what it is that makes that intolerable charge of Phyſick you mention: it is ſome years ſince, when <hi>Doctor Purſean, Doctor Bates and myſelf,</hi> for three or four vveeks attendance on a perſon of quality, received in Fees, <hi>three or four and thirty pounds,</hi> they being conſulters ſometimes only, and I ordinary Phyſitian had more than half of that ſumm; I believe my ſelf, the perſon was well, and well ſatisfyed untill the <hi>Apothecaries Bill was brought in,</hi> but then I was called to the ungrateful work of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the priſes of it, I was a little ſtarted, to find the ſumm total <hi>Five and Fifty pounds,</hi> and I do aſſure you I ſpeak moderately, when I ſay if he were paid it, his gain vvas as much as the three Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans received, but it was an <hi>Apothecary</hi> of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients own choice, and I had nothing to anſwer for it.</p>
               <p>You know Sir, by what means abroad, in many well governed States and Cities, this is alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, where the Phyſitians once a year ſet the price of all Medicines, and cauſe it to be printed, and I am afraid it was the apprehenſion of our taking up this authority here, that made the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> vvith ſo much induſtry oppoſe our Patent, and uſe us with ſo much diſreſpect before the Committee of your houſe lately; for if they had vvell and honeſtly conſidered their own intereſt, I knovv nothing vvhich could more ſolidly have advantaged them, than the <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition of the Colledge of Phyſitians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, I have been too long upon this ſixth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of yours, and therefore ſhall briefly tell you,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36531:28"/> that all the advantages of your ſeventh are better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>by Phyſittans making their own medicines,</hi> and that I cannot comply with part of your eight, becauſe no buſineſs of any great, though private concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is brought to paſs without an induſtry propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate to the acquiſition of that we contend for: They who have the eaſe they wiſh for in their private affairs, and have no concernment for the publick, will no doubt (without conſidering how things are changed now) keep the road they have been uſed too, and in vvhich they have acqnired the eaſe and advantage they enjoy, and think it perhaps juſt to do ſo, becauſe cuſtome makes the greateſt Sins no Bugbear, but they that are vvell exoited by their particular concernments, or with the deſire of doing honeſtly in their Station, will never ſcruple to uſe all ingenious induſtry to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate an honourable profeſſion, of which they are members, from the obloquie is brought upon it, by ignorance, or knavery: It is on theſe, the witts vent their virulent Scommas and reproaches; no man yet was ever reproached, for being an honeſt, able and learned Phyſitian, he that is that, and a young man, will generouſly contend for the reputation he deſerves, and never refuſe any pains to help, out of charity, the diſtreſſes of the needy; though called upon in the night to do it, his intereſt will make him riſe to help others; and it will become the elder Phyſitians, vvho are infirme, ſo much to countenance, and advantage the younger men of the Society, as to call them in to caſes, in which thoſe aſſiſtances you mention, are neceſſary to the frailties of age, or humanity; and this too, if that candor, and ingenuity be exerciſed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36531:29"/> that becomes ſuch men to uſe, may be ſo adjouſted as not to encreaſe the charge of the patient; and this vvill give better ſatisfaction in my opinion, than the ſending one, that is but breeding up to be a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, when two profeſt <hi>Phyſitians of the Colledge</hi> ſhould be ſo concerned in aſſiſting him.</p>
               <p>Your 9th conſiſts of many parts, but all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties inſinuated in it, as to the hazard, and charge a young Phyſitian, at his firſt entrance to practiſe may run, in making a competent proviſion of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, may be obviated eaſily enough, by what you inſinuate your ſelf, of remitting eaſie things, <hi>as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Decoctions, Glyſters, Ptyſans &amp;c.</hi> to the patients themſelves; which may alſo upon occaſion, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to emergent exigencies, be actuated by little quantities of generous and laſting remedies, which no Phyſitian that will attempt the way, that you or I would have but muſt alwayes have a competent <hi>Stock of,</hi> readily to ſupply the ſick with upon occaſion; and I doubt not, when you and I meet, but that I ſhall ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy you, that <hi>ſome of us have contrived a</hi> Materia medica, <hi>conſiſting of generous, laſting, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgedly, the moſt effectual known medicines;</hi> which when the trouble of making them is once over, may be contained in a Cabinet not of the largeſt ſize; and by preſent mixtures, according to the occaſion, and the help of eaſily prepared Vehicles, may ſerve as effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, as any other whatſoever, to cure all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that infect miſerable man; or at leaſt to give him all that relief, his condition is capable to receive from medicine: I cannot therefore think, that having ſome medicines made from ſhops, renders the way you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36531:29"/> propoſe better, becauſe leſs troubleſome than that of the ancients, for I am one of thoſe, that cannot va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue any trouble, that is indeed really neceſſary to the acquiring an honeſt and an honourable purpoſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides for the eaſe, and leſs trouble you mention, there are three profeſſions in Town, that may not only be better encouraged, but likewiſe be very helpful, to thoſe that would have that leſs trouble and eaſe: All the manual operations in our profeſſion, belong to the Chyrurgeons, applying Bliſters, (making iſſues, bleeding all, which the Apothecaries very often do now) and giving Glyſters (where the patient hath not the convenience of having one can give it at home) are all manual operations, and may if they will, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſome of them; <hi>The Druggiſt may as well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us, as the Apothecaries,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Diſtillers</hi> that are known honeſt, careful and able men, may be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to deſtil great quantities of thoſe waters, both ſimple, and compound, which ſhall be judged fit to be always in readineſs for uſe, and the number of thoſe I believe need not be many: And although I will allow thoſe men that will not take all the pains themſelves, all the advantages of eaſe theſe helps can give them; yet I would have every man of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, make himſelf very knowing, both in the choice and preparation of the <hi>Materia medica,</hi> that he may not eaſily be impoſed on by thoſe he buyes from.</p>
               <p>But Sir, that I may at laſt contract: All the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of your ſeven following reaſons, except that of your twelfth <hi>viz:</hi> of a <hi>Phyſitian gratifiing Apothecaries his particular Friends,</hi> are by that way I urge perfectly acquired; and that which makes me at preſent zealous for this way, is that we may the better vindicate our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36531:30"/> ſelves from thoſe durty aſperſions, theſe men before <hi>the Committee of the Houſe</hi> endeavoured to caſt upon us; we ought to let them know that as our predeceſſors inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and gave them that Trade, by which they now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and by which many have gotten fair eſtares, to wit the <hi>London Diſpenſatory,</hi> and procured them to be made a diſtinct Corporation, that they might the better apply themſelves to the knowing, and chooſing the beſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and compounding ſuch Medicines, after ſuch me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and forms, as Phyſitians judged fitteſt for practice at that time; in truſt and confidence, that they would honeſtly apply themſelves to that only, and not ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully invade, and undermine the priviledges, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of ſuch benefactors; neglecting their own honeſt duties, and deſtroying the very reaſon of their conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; which if it were an honeſt one, could be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the obviating thoſe miſchiefs, that might be done, where ordainers of medicines were the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of them likewiſe: All this I ſay conſidered, we ought to let them know, that we are not at all inferior to thoſe predeceſſors of ours, to whom they owe ſo much; but as in that <hi>Diſpenſatory</hi> they then made, they had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from a vaſt number of others, ſuch Medicines as they judged fitteſt to be ready in ſhops for the uſes they ſhould appoint them to; ſo we taught by their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and our own, (beſides the communications, we have had from the reſt of the learned World) have not onely a great proviſion of preparations, by that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the improvement of <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> hath given us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to them, but know likewiſe the defects of many of thoſe in the preſent diſpenſatory, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of many others, not then brought into uſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the various complications of diſeaſes, and the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36531:30"/> luxury, and delicacy of this latter age, having produced many new appearances of Diſeaſes, not known or taken notice of before, it hath put learned and induſtrious men, upon the invention of appropriate, and more grateful Medicines: ſo that, <hi>That Diſpenſatory of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>being almoſt grown uſeleſs, we ought to recall it, and then either keep the making of medicines to our ſelves, or elſe put it into ſuch hands, or into ſuch a method, as may render all more ſafe, both to our patients health, and our own credits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having therefore Sir, thus leaped to your 17th and laſtly, you will find me ſtill of the opinion, <hi>that all the reaſons of that propoſition are likewiſe better complyed with, and all the advantages better acquired, by the way of wholly making our own Medicines and having nothing to do with thoſe men who have uſed us ſo unkindly,</hi> provided there be preſcribed <hi>that candor, and integrity, that mutual commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and aſſiſtance, to each other of the Society, that ought to be amongſt men of a liberal and ingenuous profeſsion, and that we do really ſet our ſelves to detect all the frauds, cheats, and abuſes, that are or may be practiſed by any in the practice of Phyſick, ſo that being ſeverely honeſt our ſelves, we may cheat thoſe, that think we are not ſo;</hi> the beſt way, and if I be not much deceived my ſelf; we are a body of men at this time for the moſt part, very well qualified for ſuch an undertaking: Omitting therefore the thanks that not only my ſelf, but all of our Society owe you, for the juſt defence you have made for us, and the good opinion you have of us, <hi>I will as ſhortly as I can, offer the Reformation I would propoſe, in order to promoting all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, the facultie of Phyſick can give to mankind.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
